<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An exhortation to peace: with an intimation of the prime enemies thereof, lately delivered in a sermon, and newly published with some small addition, by Lionell Gatford, B.D. rector of Dinnington in Suffolke, now a prisoner in Ely-house in Holborne.</title>
            <author>Gatford, Lionel, d. 1665.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 88 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85833</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G333</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E94_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R2004</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861173</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861173</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113301</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A85833)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113301)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 16:E94[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An exhortation to peace: with an intimation of the prime enemies thereof, lately delivered in a sermon, and newly published with some small addition, by Lionell Gatford, B.D. rector of Dinnington in Suffolke, now a prisoner in Ely-house in Holborne.</title>
                  <author>Gatford, Lionel, d. 1665.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 29, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London printed :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: the 3 in the imprint date is crossed out; "1642 March. 24".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms CXXII, 6 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:113301:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:113301:1"/>
            <head>To the right Honourable, the Lord <hi>GORING,</hi> his ever honoured Lord,</head>
            <head type="sub">To the right Worſhipfull Sir <hi>John Rous,</hi> his moſt Noble Patron,</head>
            <head type="sub">To the vertuous Lady, the Lady <hi>Jane Covert,</hi> his liberall Benefactor,</head>
            <head type="sub">To the truly worthy and Worſhipfull, <hi>Master</hi> John Packer, <hi>his beneficent friend,</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">Lionell Gatford, B. D. &amp;c. <hi>wiſheth all happineſſe both temporall and eternall.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable, right Worſhipfull, &amp;c.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough my body be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned, yet (I bleſſe the Lord for it) my ſoule is free; ſo free, that I fear not what man can do unto me. Tis not then to begg your helpe for my inlargement, or to crave your
<pb facs="tcp:113301:2"/>ſupport under my ſufferings during my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint, that I thus addreſſe my ſelfe unto you. <hi>God is my refuge and ſtrength, a very preſent helpe in trouble; Therefore will I not feare, though the earth be moved, and though the mountaines be carried into the midſt of the Sea: though the waters thereof roare, and be troubled; though the mountaines ſhake with the ſwelling thereof, Pſal.</hi> 46. I have ſo much faith (praiſed be the Author and giver thereof) as to beleeve that ſome <hi>mountaines</hi> ſhall be <hi>removed and caſt into the Sea;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 11.24.</note> and then perhaps the Sea (as upon the caſting forth a runaway rebel, <hi>Jona.</hi> 1.) will ceaſe from her raging. But whether ſhe doe or not, I truſt I ſhall never be of ſo little faith, as over-much to be afraid of mine owne ſinking. The true reaſon of my flying to you at this preſent, is, in plain tearmes, this: What externals ſoever I either now poſſeſſe, or have hitherto ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted by, I have received from God by the hands of one, or more, of you; and therefore before I am denuded or ſpoyled
<pb facs="tcp:113301:2"/>of what I have (which ſome have threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned) I would have the world know where I had it; otherwiſe, I ſhould ſuſpect that my ingratitude might betray it into their hands that are ready to catch at it. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing I confeſſe I have by your meanes, though from the ſame fountaine, more then is viſible; and ſome thanks I muſt reſerve for you, more then is expreſſable. This poore, but ſincere (Exhortation to Peace, ſent forth in theſe times of tumultuous in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrections, will, I hope, render me to you, and to all that ſhall chance to peruſe it, a true Sonne of Peace, and a peaceable Son of Truth. And if no other return ſhould be made you for what ye have adventured in ſo weake a veſſell, I am confident yee would not thinke it loſt; ſo intirely doe ye love, and ſo highly doe yee priſe both thoſe graces, in whomſoever you finde them. But if God ſhall vouchſafe, amongſt many petitioners, to heare my prayers for Peace, you ſhall be ſure to feele that I am a Sonne of Prayer too, by the bleſſing of
<pb facs="tcp:113301:3"/>Peace, which I ſhall never ceaſe to pray for, upon you and all yours, with as many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as love the peace of our Jeruſalem. And this I am aſſured ye will accept as the proper retribution of a poor priſoner, and</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your bond-ſervant, <hi>L. G.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>Page 5. line 14. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> read <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. p. 8. l. laſt, dele of. p. 9. l. 8. for rag r. ray. p. 12. l. 3. for as frees any ſuit, r. if they can finde any ſuch. p. 13. l. 5. for promiſe r. premiſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:113301:3"/>
            <head>To all the Sonnes of Peace throughout the divided Kingdome of <hi>England:</hi> Lionell Gatford <hi>B. D. &amp;c.</hi> wiſheth <hi>Grace, mercy and peace from God the Father of peace, and from our Lord Ieſus Chriſt the purchaſer and finiſher of our peace.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen the ſound of a civill warre within the bowels of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome firſt tingled mine ears, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing neither <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> nor <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, neither without naturall affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on nor without Chriſtian com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, I could not but take up to my ſelfe the Prophets ſympathizing complaint, <hi>Jerem.</hi> 4.19, 20. <hi>My bowels my bowels, I am pained at the very heart, my heart maketh a noiſe in me, I cannot hold my peace, becauſe thou haſt heard O my ſoule, the ſound of the trumpet, the alarm of war, deſtruction upon deſtruction is cried, for the whole Land is spoyled, &amp;c.</hi> But then knowing my ſelf to be <hi>ſet a watchman</hi> to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and ſo the crying to, or within my ſelfe alone, when I <hi>ſaw the ſword come,</hi> would not excuſe me, but that I ſtood obliged to <hi>lift up my voice like a trumpet</hi> and <hi>to give others warning thereof,</hi> or elſe their <hi>blood would be required at my hands, Ezek.</hi> 33.6. <hi>(And what wil it profit a man,
<note place="margin">Proſper.</note> non pro ſuo puniri peccato qui puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endus eſt alieno; not to be puniſh'd for his own ſin who ſhal be condemned for anothers)</hi> I began to caſt about, how I
<pb facs="tcp:113301:4"/>beſt <hi>deliver mine own ſoule</hi> by helping to ſave others.</p>
            <p>Whereupon, obſerving, that not ſo much the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular miſunderſtanding each other in ſeverall paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages and meſſages betwixt the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>His great Councell,</hi> as the Generall not-underſtanding of the Subjects loyalty and obedience to their Sovereigne, clouded by the fogs and miſts of falſe teachers, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haled from the bogs and creekes of Anabaptiſts and other Sectaries, had both begotten and nurſed up our miſeries to that height of growth, whereunto they are now come; I reſolved, as well for the free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mine owne ſoule from the guilt of others blood, as for the preventing others from further embrew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their hands in the blood of their Chriſtian Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, faithfully to impart to this whole Nation, not mine owne private opinion, but the <hi>publike received Doctrine of this whole Church, and the harmonious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the moſt eminent Members thereof, as alſo the publike Doctrine and unanimous conſent of other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches, and many renowned Worthies therein, concerning the Right, Power, Honour and Dignity, of Kings and ſovereigne Princes, and the loyalty and obedience due unto them from all their Subjects; together with a diſcovery of who and what ſort of men have been the prime disturbers of Peace, and rayſers of Rebellion, ſince the firſt ſhining forth of the glorious light of the Gospell, in thoſe places especially where the Gospell hath been propagated; as alſo a ſupplement of ſatisfying anſwers to the maine arguments and objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, wherby the enemies of this Kingdom and their own peace, would evade whatſoever is aſſerted againſt them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this my intention was fruſtrated; for on <hi>Jan.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:113301:4"/>26. <hi>in the night, Maſter Crumwell,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job 24.16.</note> a Member of the Houſe of Commons, ſeized upon the Coppy of that Tractat compoſed by me for that purpoſe, as it was then in the preſſe at <hi>Cambridge,</hi> and fifteen or ſixteen ſheets thereof printed, and the ſame <hi>night with his Troopes he apprehended my perſon</hi> quietly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in <hi>Jeſus-Colledge,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 22.13.</note> which with the Coppy he tranſmitted hither to <hi>London,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Act. 25.27.</note> 
               <hi>on the next Lords day</hi> following, and on munday <hi>Jan.</hi> 30, I was by the Honourable Houſe of Commons committed priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to <hi>Ely-Houſe,</hi> where I am ſtill reſtreined <hi>without any charge againſt me,</hi> that I can yet heare of.</p>
            <p>Now remembring holy <hi>Jeremiahs</hi> practiſe,
<note place="margin">Jerem. 36.</note> who when he was <hi>ſhut up in priſon,</hi> thought not that an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe ſufficient for not making known to the people thoſe things which concerned them, but ſent forth <hi>a roll, written from his owne mouth, to be read in the eares of all Judah;</hi> I could not ſatisfie my conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence quickened with ſo good an example, and incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged with Gods gracious deliverance of him that ſet it, till I had ſent abroad ſomething, whereby I might in ſome part informe the people of this Land of their duty, and diſcharge mine owne; and have<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nothing in a readineſſe (now that my former in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended treatiſe is ſtrangled in the birth) ſo ſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and ſuitable for theſe tumultuous and diſtracted times, as this exhortation to peace, I have adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured that amongſt you.</p>
            <p>You will finde it indeed flatly oppoſite, nay fully contradictorie to multitudes of exhortations, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with not onely our <hi>parlours</hi> are peſtered,
<note place="margin">2 Tim. 3. v. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6.</note> but our very Pulpits are profaned in theſe <hi>perilous times.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:113301:5"/>It muſt therfore be your care with thoſe <hi>noble Bere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Act.</hi> 17. <hi>to ſearch the Scripturs daily, whether thoſe things</hi> affirmed by thoſe <hi>Salij</hi> or <hi>Prieſts of Mars</hi> in their <hi>skipping vociſerations,</hi> or theſe avouched by me a <hi>Miniſter of peace</hi> in this ſlow-paced Sermon, be according to what is there recorded or not.</p>
            <p>For my part I challenge nothing to my ſelfe, but weakneſſe and unworthineſſe; but by the grace of God I am what I am, and to the praiſe and glory of his free grace be it aſcribed, I have ever been ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxall in judgement, and conformable in practiſe, to the eſtabliſhed doctrine and diſcipline of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> without ſwarving or digreſſing therefrom, either to ſerve the times though never ſo turbulent, or to obſerve mens humors though never ſo potent, during freely to reprove corruption and innovation in Religion and religious worſhip, where I met with any ſuch, when the <hi>Stentors</hi> or <hi>Baaling</hi> cryers of theſe times durſt not mutter againſt them, and alwayes labouring (though compaſſed about with many imperfections) to adorne Religion and the profeſſion therof by faithfulneſſe in my calling, and by unſtainedneſſe of life and converſation.</p>
            <p>But for thoſe, whoſe doctrine and practiſes this Sermon oppugnes; They bragge much of their <hi>light,</hi> bring them therfore into the <hi>light; To the Law and to the Teſtimony, and if they speake not according to this word, it is becauſe ther's no light in them, Iſa.</hi> 8.20. and <hi>he that ſaith he is in the light and hateth his brother, he is in darkneſſe even untill now,</hi> 1 <hi>Joh</hi> 2.9.</p>
            <p>They boaſt likewiſe that they, and onely they, have the <hi>spirit;</hi> But <hi>beloved, beleeve not every spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,
<pb facs="tcp:113301:5"/>but try the spirits whether they are of God: becauſe many falſe prophets are gone out into the world,</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.1. If they have the <hi>spirit</hi> you ſhall know it by the <hi>fruit</hi> thereof. Now <hi>the fruit of the spirit is love, joy, peace, long-ſuffering, gentleneſſe, goodneſſe, faith, meekneſſe, temperance, Galat.</hi> 5.22, 23.</p>
            <p>They deſire alſo to make you beleeve, what it ſeemes by <hi>Jobs</hi> anſwer, <hi>Cap.</hi> 12.2. his <hi>miſerable comforters</hi> would have aſſumed to themſelves, that all wiſdome is with them, yea, and <hi>ſhall die with them,</hi> if they miſcarry; nay, their very folly and madneſſe is ſtiled by themſelves and their Favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites, <hi>spirituall wiſdome:</hi> But the word of God will try that too; For <hi>the wiſdome that is from above is first pure, then peaceable, gentle, eaſie to be entreated, full of mercy and good fruits, without partiality, and without hypocriſie, James</hi> 3.17.</p>
            <p>For their <hi>holineſſe</hi> and <hi>righteouſneſſe</hi> none mayque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion it without the cenſure of being a reprobate, for ſuch a preſumption; and yet the Scripture is a touchſtone that will prove the truth of that alſo, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by their love to peace: For <hi>the fruit of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe ſaith Saint Iames, is ſowne in peace of them that make peace, Cap.</hi> 3. <hi>v.</hi> 18. And <hi>where envying and ſtrife is,</hi> (much more where war and bloodſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding is) <hi>there is confuſion and every evill work, v.</hi> 16. And <hi>from whence come wars and fightings among you?</hi> (ſaith the ſame Apoſtle) <hi>come they not hence, even of your luſts, that warre in your members? Cap.</hi> 4. <hi>v.</hi> 1. But if you would ſee the holy warre of the preſent times lively ſet forth, read on, v. 2, 3. <hi>Ye luſt and have not, ye kill, and deſire to have, and cannot obtaine; ye
<pb facs="tcp:113301:6"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:113301:6"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:113301:7"/>fight and warre, yet ye have not becauſe ye aske not; ye aske and receive not, becauſe ye ask amiſſe, that ye may conſume it upon your lusts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In a word thoſe new teachers, or teachers of newes (as the moſt of them deſerve to be ſtiled) would fain dreame you into an opinion, that they are for <hi>peace,</hi> as much, or more then any, onely they would have <hi>peace</hi> with <hi>truth.</hi> But who can beleeve them? when they <hi>make lies their reſuge,</hi> and daily wreſt and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert the <hi>Word of truth</hi> to encourage to warre: with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>peace, truth</hi> cannot be eſtabliſhed, and ſo long as the people are <hi>given over to beleeve their lies,</hi> 'tis impoſſible that <hi>peace</hi> ſhould be obtained. Nay, had they been <hi>men of truth,</hi> neither <hi>peace</hi> nor <hi>truth</hi> had been now unſetled, much leſſe ſhattered into ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny peices, as that it will be difficult to repaire ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and no leſſe then a miracle to reſtore both to their former ſplendor and glory. Had your Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers dealt <hi>truly</hi> with you, I ſhould not have needed to have ſent this ſermon of <hi>peace</hi> at this time amongſt you; for if ſome of them, when they were conſulted by you (as that I preſume they were) concerning the lawfulneſſe of the preſent war, had not with thoſe lying Prophets 1 <hi>King.</hi> 22. encouraged to battell, with a <hi>Goe and prosper, for the Lord ſhall deliver,</hi> not the <hi>City</hi> into the <hi>Kings hands,</hi> but the <hi>King</hi> into the hands of the <hi>City;</hi> certainly our <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> had ſtill enjoyed her bleſſed <hi>peace,</hi> and all that love her <hi>peace</hi> had ſtill flowriſhed in their envied <hi>prosperity.</hi> I am no accuſer of my brethren, but if <hi>from the prophets of Jeruſalem,</hi> as the Lord once complained by that holy prophet <hi>Jerem.</hi> 23.15. <hi>prophaneſſe or hypocriſie,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:113301:7"/>(for Gods Name is never more prophaned then by hypocriticall prophets) <hi>be gone forth into all the land,</hi> and both <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> and the whole <hi>Land</hi> be ready to be ruined thereby; I conceive I have authority ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient even from the <hi>Prophet Jeremy</hi> to complain of ſuch <hi>Prophets,</hi> and that before the people, that ſo the people may yet at laſt beware of them; onely this I muſt tell the people, thoſe filthy dreamers, (as Saint <hi>Jude</hi> cals them) thoſe falſe prophets (as the deceived people themſelves will ere long acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge them) who <hi>defile the fleſh, despiſe dominion and speake evill of dignities, Jude Epiſt. v.</hi> 8. teaching others to doe the like, doe but <hi>dreame ſuch dreames</hi> as <hi>the people have cauſed to be dreamed Jerem.</hi> 29.8. and although <hi>the prophet be a ſoole, and the spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all man mad,</hi> yet the <hi>people</hi> muſt remember, that 'tis for the <hi>multitudes of their iniquity, and their great hatred, Hoſea</hi> 9.7. Either the people being a <hi>rebellious people, lying children, children that will not heare the law of the Lord, Iſa.</hi> 30.9. have ſaid <hi>to the Seers ſee not, and to the Prophets propheſie not unto us right things, v.</hi> 10. Or elſe they have ſhewn themſelves too well pleaſed with them when they have ſo propheſied; but not a word more now ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Prophets or people in that way. I am to preſent you with an Exhortation to Peace, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſhall avoid as much as I can whatſoever may exaſperate any that are <hi>peaceably</hi> inclined. The <hi>Prophets, Prieſts, Princes and people of Jeruſalem,</hi> had all of them ſinned highly againſt God, and ſo provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked him, that he had made a breach amongſt them, which threatned utter deſtruction unto them, as you
<pb facs="tcp:113301:8"/>may read at large, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 22. And yet God of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite mercy was pleaſed <hi>to ſeek,</hi> and to ſeek but for <hi>one man amongſt them</hi> all, to <hi>make up the hedge, and ſtand in the gap before him, for the Land, that he ſhould not deſtroy it, v.</hi> 30. How then ſhould we of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, notwithſtanding all our ſins of <hi>Prophets, Prieſts, Princes,</hi> and <hi>people,</hi> ſo reſembling <hi>Judah's,</hi> as if cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pied out by them (our rebellion onely excepted, wherein we exceed both them and the moſt of other Nations) how ſhould we be encouraged to ſeeke to God to have our breaches made up, and to approach <hi>boldly</hi> unto the <hi>Throne of his grace,
<note place="margin">Heb. 3.1.</note> that we may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine mercy, and ſinde grace to help in time of need?</hi> How ſhould we be quickned in our prayers, and beſt endeavours for the <hi>peace</hi> of our <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> when the prayers and endeavours of one man is ſo prevalent with God, for the making peace for a whole Nation, and for the averting deſtruction from it? Whether our prayers prevaile with God for the <hi>peace</hi> of our <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> or not, we our ſelves that ſo <hi>love Jeruſalem</hi> as to <hi>pray for the peace thereof,</hi> are ſure to <hi>prosper;</hi> we have Gods Word for it in our Text. To our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers then, to our prayers with all poſſible conſtancy and fervency, and ſo to the Sermon with all due re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence and ſubmiſſion, humbly beſeeching our moſt gracious God, whoſe Word is here tendred us, to make this his Word ſo effectuall to us all, that it may help to make us to pray more and more effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually for <hi>Jeruſalems peace,</hi> on which depends all our proſperity, <hi>Amen, Amen.</hi> 
            </p>
            <closer>So prayes <signed>A priſoner of the Lord, and your daily Orator, <hi>Lionell Gatford.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>Ely-houſe, <date>Feb. 1642.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:113301:8"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Text. PSAL. 122. verſ. 6.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Pray for the Peace of Jeruſalem; they ſhall proſper that love thee.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE <hi>Scriptures</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Paul</hi>) <hi>are able to make a man wiſe unto ſalvation,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15. <hi>Liber pſalmorum, &amp;c.</hi> The Booke of Pſalmes (ſaith Saint <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi>) comprehends in it as in an epito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, or abſtract, whatſoever neceſſary things all other books of Scripture con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain at large. Now amongſt the Pſalmes the Pſalmes of degrees are by many accounted Pſalms of ſome degrees of excellency above other Pſames; and amongſt the Pſames of degrees (if there may be <hi>comparatio gradus ad gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum,</hi> a comparing of a degree with a degree, where each Pſalme is in its degree ſo admirable) this Pſalme of degrees out of which my Text is taken is none of the loweſt degree. The text it ſelfe. I am ſure is one of the ſweeteſt and pleaſanteſt ſtraines in all the Pſames. For what more delightfull and pleaſing to God then <hi>prayer? the prayer of the upright</hi> (ſaith <hi>Salomon</hi>) <hi>is Gods delight, Pro.</hi> 15.8. and <hi>let my prayer,</hi> ſaith <hi>David, be ſet forth before thee as incenſe, Pſal.</hi> 141.2. that is let it aſcend as a ſweet perfume and pleaſant ſmell into thy noſtrils; it being the peculiar honour of prayer (as <hi>Dioniſius Carthuſianus</hi> hath obſerved) to have the ſtile of <hi>incenſe</hi> attributed to it, for <hi>nulla
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:113301:9"/>justatia</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>thumiamits comparatur niſi ſola oratio,</hi> No other theologicall vertue is compared to incenſe, but onely prayer, at leaſt not ſo properly. And this we finde incited unto in the firſt word of my text, <hi>pray, pray, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe, as nothing is more delightfull and pleaſing to God then <hi>Prayer,</hi> ſo nothing is more ſweet and acceptable to men (except they be <hi>men of Belial</hi>) then <hi>Peace, Pax non re duntaxat amica, ſed nomine quoque ipſo jucunda,</hi> ſaith <hi>Nazianzen, Peace</hi> is not onely lovely in the thing, but pleaſant alſo in the very name; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſaith <hi>Baſil,</hi> the abſoluteſt of Bleſſings; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> there is no Bleſſing equall to <hi>Peace;</hi> and the Scriptures make good what they all ſay by putting <hi>Peace</hi> ſo often for all Bleſſings, as comprehending all other Bleſſings in the boſome of it, as amongſt other places, Pſal. 125.5. <hi>But peace ſhall be upon Iſrael;</hi> and Pſal. 29.11. <hi>The Lord will bleſſe his people with peace:</hi> or as the ordinary tranſlation reads it: <hi>The Lord ſhall give his people the Bleſſing of peace.</hi> In both which places the word tranſlated, <hi>Peace,</hi> as expoſitors have obſerved, <hi>non tantum pacem ſed reliqua bona omnia complectatur et corpori et animo neceſſaria,</hi> doth not only comprehend <hi>peace</hi> within it's ſignification, but all other good things whatſoever neceſſary both for body and ſoule, as it doth alſo in ſundry other places of Scripture. And this we are called upon here in my Text to pray for; pray for the <hi>peace, &amp;c. The peace,</hi> what <hi>peace?</hi> not the peace of <hi>Babylon</hi> (though when the <hi>Jews</hi> were delivered into the hands of the King of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and carried away captive thither, they were commanded both to <hi>ſeek the peace</hi> of that City and to <hi>pray for it, Jerem.</hi> 29.7.) but the <hi>Peace</hi> that our text exhorts to pray for, is the <hi>Peace of Jeruſalem;</hi> that is, according to the literall ſenſe, the <hi>Peace</hi> of that City which the <hi>Lord</hi> hath <hi>choſen among all the tribes of Iſrael to place his name there,</hi> 2 <hi>Chr.</hi> 6. as alſo to place the <hi>throne of David,</hi> and ſo of juſtice and judgement there, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 5.5. both expreſſed in the three immediate verſes before my Text, as arguments to make way for the praying for the peace there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. <hi>Jeruſalem is builded as a City, that is compact together,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:113301:9"/>whither the tribes go up the tribes of the Lord, unto the teſtimony of Iſrael, to give thanks unto the Name of the Lord; for there are ſet thrones of judgement, the thrones of the houſe of</hi> David, then followes <hi>pray for the peace of Jeruſalem, &amp;c.</hi> Or els by the <hi>peace of Jeruſalem,</hi> we may underſtand here, according to the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall ſenſe of the words, the peace of Gods Church, in what Cities or Nations ſoever it be planted; called <hi>Jeruſalem which is above and the mother of us all, Gal.</hi> 4.26. <hi>the City of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God, the heavenly Ieruſalem, Heb.</hi> 12.22. and that not without alluſion to that and the like propheſie of preaching the Goſpell, <hi>Eſay</hi> 2.3. <hi>Out of Sion ſhall goe forth the Law, and the Word of the Lord from Ieruſalem:</hi> that is the Goſpell ſhall firſt be preached, and ſo the Church firſt planted in <hi>Ieruſalem;</hi> and from thence the Goſpell ſhall be publiſhed, and ſo the Church tranſplanted in all the world: and therefore the Church having her firſt riſe, and beginning from <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> ſhe might well beare <hi>Ieruſalems</hi> name. <hi>Pray for the peace of Ieruſalem.</hi> I had once thought to have opened the other part of the Text, ere I had let you further into the treaſurie of this: but me thinks I ſee you impatient of being kept off any longer, from taſting of theſe rarities which have been already preſented be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you: I forbeare therefore all ſuper-addition of arguments to invite your attention to the Text, and fall cloſe to the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bowelling of it. The Text at the firſt touch fals into two parts; a <hi>Precept</hi> and a <hi>Promiſe.</hi> The <hi>precept</hi> in the firſt words, <hi>pray for the Peace of Jeruſalem.</hi> The <hi>promiſe</hi> in the following words, <hi>they ſhall prosper that love thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the <hi>precept</hi> theſe five particulars offer themſelves to our conſideration. 1. The <hi>Act</hi> or <hi>Duty</hi> commanded; and that is to <hi>pray. Pray &amp;c.</hi> 2. The <hi>object</hi> of that <hi>Act;</hi> and that is <hi>peace, Pray for the peace.</hi> 3. The <hi>Specification</hi> or <hi>determination</hi> of that <hi>object;</hi> not for all <hi>peace,</hi> nor the <hi>peace</hi> of all; but for the <hi>Peace of Ieruſalem. Pray for the Peace of Ieruſalem.</hi> 4. The <hi>par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty by whom</hi> this <hi>precept</hi> is delivered; and that, as the title of the Pſalme ſhewes, is <hi>David. David</hi> the King of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> take <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> in the letter; but <hi>David</hi> the ſonne or citizen of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:113301:10"/>
               <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> take <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> in the miſterie. 5. The <hi>party unto whom</hi> this precept is recommended; and they are no where expreſſed, but fully implyed in the word <hi>precamini,</hi> or <hi>rogate, pray ye:</hi> all <hi>ye</hi> that have any intereſt in or relation to <hi>Ieruſalem, pray for the Peace thereof;</hi> ſo farre the <hi>precept</hi> extends: but the <hi>promiſe</hi> reacheth further, and fetcheth in all thoſe that love proſperity, aſſuring them that they ſhall all <hi>prosper</hi> that ſo love <hi>Ieruſalem:</hi> wherein three other particulars require our obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. 1. The <hi>ſubject matter</hi> of the <hi>promiſe;</hi> and that's <hi>Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; they ſhall prosper.</hi> 2. The <hi>condition</hi> of the <hi>promiſe;</hi> and that is, the loving <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> ſo as to <hi>pray</hi> for her <hi>peace; they ſhall prosper that love thee.</hi> 3. The <hi>extent</hi> of the <hi>promiſe,</hi> collected from the perſons unto whom this promiſe is made; namely, <hi>they,</hi> and all <hi>they,</hi> and onely <hi>they,</hi> that ſo love <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> as to <hi>pray for</hi> the <hi>Peace</hi> thereof.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the parts of the Text, and theſe are the particulars of each part: but for feare leſt the Text might loſe ſome of its ſtrength and virtue, by being chopt into ſo many ſmall pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. I ſhall forbear the proſecuting that diviſion and ſubdiviſion, and chooſe rather to give you the juce and ſubſtance, if not, the ſpirit and quinteſſence of all theſe particulars, in theſe 4 propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions.</p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>That the peace of</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>is a thing moſt deſirable, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of the best prayers, and the prayers of the beſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>That the prime meanes, both of procuring and preſerving the peace of</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>is to pray for it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>That it is the duty of all men, that have any intereſt in or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>to pray for the peace thereof themſelves, and to incite others to doe the like.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4 <hi>That they, and all they, and onely they ſhall prosper, that ſo love</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>as to pray for the peace thereof,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I begin with the firſt propoſition: <hi>That the peace of</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>is a thing moſt deſirable, worthy of the beſt prayers, and prayers of the beſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This propoſition I ſhall endeavour to make good, both ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the literall, and according to the miſticall accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:113301:10"/>of this terme <hi>Ieruſalem;</hi> and firſt according to the literall.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>The peace of</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>as</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>is taken for the place of Gods worſhip, and the ſeat of juſtice, and judgement, was then, and ſo is, the peace of all ſuch places ſtill, a moſt deſirable thing worthy of the beſt prayers &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tantum est pacis bonum</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Auguſtine lib.</hi> 19. <hi>de Civitate Det cap.</hi> 11.) <hi>ut etiam in rebus terrenis atque mortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus nihil gratius ſolcat audiri, nihil deſiderabilius concupiſci, ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil poſſit melius inven<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ri;</hi> ſuch is the good of Peace, that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt earthly and tranſitory things, nothing is to be heard of more acceptable, nothing is to be wiſhed for more deſirable, nothing can be found out more excellent. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<note place="margin">Chryſoſ ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 3. in Coloſſ.</note> (ſaith Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi>) the mother of all good things, are the ground of all joy: and as there is no man <hi>qui gaudere nolit,</hi> who would not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce; ſo there is no man <hi>qui parem habere nolit,</hi> who would not have peace, is Saint <hi>Auguſtines</hi> poſition in the <hi>booke</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore cited <hi>cap.</hi> 12. and he there makes it good: and 'tis ſo good what he there ſaith, that I thinke it worthy both of our repeating and obſerving, <hi>ipſi qui bella volunt</hi> (ſaith that ſtout Champion of the Church) <hi>nihil aliud quam vincere volunt,</hi> they that moſt deſire warres, doe therefore deſire them that may conquer and overcome: and ſo in the upſhot, they deſire wars that may obtaine a more glorious <hi>peace:</hi> for what is victory or conqueſt, but the ſubduing and bringing into ſubjection thoſe that oppoſe and reſiſt? and what is that when it is accompliſhed, but very peace? ſo that warres themſelves are waged upon an intention of <hi>peace,</hi> and <hi>peace</hi> is the deſired end of all warres. They which doe moſt diſturbe the <hi>peace</hi> which they enjoy, and therefore are accounted enemies of <hi>peace,</hi> yea of their owne <hi>peace,</hi> they doe not ſo properly hate <hi>peace,</hi> as deſire to exchange one <hi>peace</hi> for another; neither would they that there ſhould be no <hi>peace</hi> at all, but that ſuch a <hi>peace</hi> ſhould be as they would. The moſt factious, ſeditious fellowes that are, though out of their factious, ſeditious ſpirits, they ſeperate themſelves from
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:113301:11"/>ſociety and <hi>peace</hi> with others; yet with their fellow-conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, they obſerve and keep an exact kind of <hi>peace,</hi> or elſe they could never improve their conſpiracies to ſo much miſchiefes as they doe. Theeves and robbers could not either with the leaſt ſafety or ſucceſſe, infect and trouble the <hi>peace</hi> of others, unleſſe they did preſerve a firme ſeeming <hi>peace</hi> amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: or if there be any ſuch beaſt of prey, that is either ſo powerfull in ſtrength, or ſo fearfull by nature, that he need not, or dare not commit himſelfe to any companion, but plots and acts all his robberies and other outrages himſelfe alone, yet in his owne houſe, with his owne family, he ſtudies <hi>peace</hi> and qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etnes; and if any diſturbance chance therin, none more forward, then he to correct and vindicate it, <hi>domus ſuae pacem ſi ita ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe eſt</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> of ſuch a one) <hi>etiam ſaeviendo componit,</hi> he compoſeth the peace of his houſe, if it be needfull ſo to doe, even by tyrannizing and exerciſing cruelty on thoſe that infringed it. Nay, I will crave leave to ſtep one ſtep fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with that father; let us for once ſuppoſe ſuch a monſter as the <hi>Poets</hi> faigned their <hi>Cacus</hi> to be, whom for his inſociable ſavageneſſe they called <hi>ſemi hominem non hominem,</hi> but halfe a man not a man; one <hi>cujus regnum dirae ſpeluncae fuerit ſolitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do,</hi> whoſe loneſomeneſſe in a direfull cave was his Kingdome, and whoſe wickedneſſe was ſo beyond other men's, that like the Divell he had his name from it;
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> one that tooke pleaſure neither in the winning ſociety of a wife, nor in the recreating ſports of children; one that would neither rule over others, nor enter conference with them; one that would give nothing to any, but take from all whatſoever he could, and could take whatſoever he pleaſed; yet this horrid monſter ſo abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring all <hi>peace</hi> with others, does by his very ſolitarineſſe and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation of all ſociety, declare plainly that freedome from all moleſtation, and ſo <hi>peace,</hi> is the prime ſcope and aime of all his deſires. And that I make not a fiction the uppermoſt ſtep of my gradation, ſuffer me to tell you that the very devils themſelves, what inveterate, implacable cruelty ſoever they beare againſt the <hi>peace</hi> of men, amongſt themſelves they conſpire for <hi>peace,</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:113301:11"/>and doe to all admiration conſerve it: <hi>Satan is not divided a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſatan, Marke</hi> 3. and a whole legion of devils can dwell together, as one in one man, <hi>Marke</hi> 5.9. Nothing therefore is naturally more deſirable then <hi>peace,</hi> and there is none that hath all the impreſſions of nature ſo defaced in him, but that ſome <hi>peace</hi> or other is beloved and deſired of him; how much more deſirable then, <hi>is the peace of Jeruſalem,</hi> as 'tis the place of Gods worſhip and ſervice, and the ſeat of juſtice and judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to all thoſe that love either? Where there is no <hi>peace,</hi> the publike worſhip and ſervice of God doth not onely loſe its beauty and comlineſſe, but ſuffers much in its very eſſence and being. <hi>One thing</hi> (ſaies <hi>David) have I deſired of the Lord that I will ſeek after, that I may dwell in the houſe of the Lord al the dayes of my life, to behold the beauty of the Lord &amp; viſit his temple, or enquire in his temple, Pſal.</hi> 27.4. but becauſe <hi>David</hi> was <hi>a man of warre,</hi> and the time of his reigne a time of warre, he never could obtaine this his deſire in any perfection, though he were moſt zealous and earneſt in it. <hi>David</hi> never ſo much as thought of building an houſe unto the Lord, till he had ſome reſpite from warre as appeares, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.1, 2. &amp;c. and when he did thinke on it, God, who knew his thoughts, knew alſo that it was in a manner to no purpoſe for him, upon whom warres were preſently to returne, to undertake that worke; for neither could that worke it ſelfe be ſo well effected in ſuch times nor the publike worſhip of God in that houſe if it ſhould be built, be neer ſo wel performed as it would be in more peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able times. And therefore obſerve how the Lord took off <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> from thoſe thoughts, as <hi>David</hi> himſelfe relates it to his ſonne <hi>Solomon,</hi> 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 22. v. 7.8.9.10. <hi>And David ſaid to</hi> Solomon, <hi>my ſon, as for me, it was in my mind to build an houſe unto the Name of the Lord my God; but the Word of the Lord came to me ſaying, thou haſt ſhed blood abundantly, and haſt made great warres; thou ſhalt not build an houſe unto my name, becauſe thou haſt ſhed much blood upon the earch in my ſight, behold a ſonne ſhall be borne unto thee, who ſhall be a man of reſt, and I will give him reſt from all his enemies round about; for
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:113301:12"/>his name ſhall be</hi> Solomon, <hi>and I will give peace and quietneſſe to I frael in his dayes, he ſhall build an houſe for my Name, &amp;c.</hi> Behold <hi>David, a man of warre,</hi> though a <hi>man after Gods owne heart.</hi> and his warres no other then what God had approved; he was inhibited the building of an <hi>houſe</hi> for Gods publike wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and ſervice, onely for this reaſon; <hi>becauſe he had ſhed much blood and made great warres;</hi> whereas the bloody reformers of theſe times cry up the laying of the foundation of their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of Gods publike worſhip in ſervice in nothing but blood, &amp; that the blood of thoſe who profeſſe the worſhipping and ſerving of God in that publike manner, and way; for the ſounding and erecting whereof, many renowned Mattyres were willing to loſe their blood; ſo ſarre are <hi>their thoughts</hi> from <hi>Gods thoughts,</hi> and <hi>their wayes</hi> from <hi>Gods wayes.</hi> Obſerve further, how God (to cleare his owne reaſon, of forbidding <hi>David</hi> to build him an houſe, that it was therefore &amp; therefore onely, becauſe he had made great warres and ſhed much blood) at the ſame time, when he inhibited <hi>David</hi> for that cauſe, he gave commandement to his Sonne <hi>Solomon to build him an houſe for his name,</hi> and alleadgeth the juſt contrary reaſon for that command, viz. <hi>becauſe he ſhould be a man of peace and reſt,</hi> and one unto whom God promiſed that he would <hi>give reſt from his enemies round about,</hi> and <hi>give peace and quietneſſe to Iſrael in his dayes.</hi> And he indeed undertooke this worke and ſo proſpered in it, that he finiſhed it in ſeven yeeres. 1 <hi>Kin.</hi> 6.38. The inferences from hence are many and various ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the apprehenſion of ſeverall Expoſitors; but all that I ſhall urge from hence, is but what I have already toucht, That God by the very time appointed by him for the building of his Temple, the place of his publique worſhip and ſervice, ſignifies unto us, that times of peace are the onely times for his publike worſhip and ſervice it ſelfe, and that warres, though never ſo juſt, doe not onely hinder it but doe in a manner, yea and in a great meaſure to, prophane it: and what I ſay of the times of peace and warre, muſt of neceſſity reach to the places where peace or warres ſettle; and therefore as the <hi>houſe</hi> for
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:113301:12"/>Gods publike worſhip and ſervice, was at firſt built in time of peace, ſo 'twas built in a City of peace in <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> which is by interpretation <hi>the viſion of peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God may, I confeſſe, be worſhipped and ſerved publikely in ſome Camps or Leagers, yea in the <hi>midſt of Marſ-hill</hi> (as 'tis ſaid, Saint <hi>Paul</hi> once preacht, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.23.) But alas the worſhip and ſervice, that is uſually performed unto God in ſuch places, hath ſcarce a rag of that beauty and ſplendor, or a ſpark of that zeale and vigour, wherewith it is adorned and inclined in places of <hi>peace,</hi> unleſſe they be ſuch places of <hi>peace,</hi> as doe not <hi>know what belong to their peace,</hi> which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> her ſelfe ſometimes did not, <hi>Luk.</hi> 19.42.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>How beautifull upon the mountaines</hi> (ſaith the <hi>Prophet) are feete of him that bringeth good tidings, that publiſheth peace, Iſa.</hi> 52.7. The <hi>Apoſtle</hi> appplies that ſaying to the Preachers of the Goſpell, <hi>Fom.</hi> 10.15. <hi>How beautifull are the feet of them that preach the Gospell of peace, &amp;c.</hi> The <hi>beauty</hi> and excellency of preaching the <hi>Gospell</hi> is ſuch, as neither the <hi>Prophet</hi> nor the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> could expreſſe, and therefore they cry out in admiration thereof, <hi>quam specioſi pedes, &amp;c. how beautifull are the feet of him</hi> or them, that <hi>publiſh</hi> or <hi>preach peace;</hi> and as there is <hi>beauty</hi> in the publike preaching the <hi>Gospell,</hi> ſo there is <hi>beauty</hi> in the publike <hi>praying</hi> unto God, and praiſing of him, as alſo in the reſt of Gods publike wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and ſervice rightly performed; and therefore is the whole worſhip and ſervice of God in his <hi>houſe</hi> called, (as you heard but now) by the kingly Prophet <hi>David, the beauty of the Lord Pſa.</hi> 27. and <hi>the beauty of holineſſe Pſal.</hi> 29.2. But beloved in what places is this <hi>beauty</hi> and excellency of Gods worſhip and ſervice to be found? Not in thoſe places where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſound of the trumpet, and alarme of warre are daily heard; for what agreement hath the preaching of the <hi>Goſpell of peace</hi> with warring and fighting, or what entertainment can <hi>praying</hi> finde, where killing and murthering are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, and who can hope to heare the voice of <hi>praiſing God,</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:113301:13"/>where curſing and blaſpheming his Name are ſo uncontrol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledly practiſed? 'tis a ſhort but a ſmart and pithy examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Souldiers <hi>Pater-Noſter,</hi> which <hi>Eraſmus</hi> takes in his <hi>Querimoniae pacis,</hi> I will adde but a little to it, and by it you may gueſſe how God is worſhipped and ſerved in thoſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, where ſuch men keepe their Randevooze; <hi>quid quaeſo orat miles,</hi> what, I beſeech you (ſaith <hi>Eraſmus</hi>) does the Souldier pray, or how? Doeſt thou ſay <hi>Our Father?</hi> O im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent mouth! doeſt thou dare to call God father, who art flying at the throate of thy brother to cut it or teare it out? Doeſt thou ſay, <hi>hallowed be Thy Name,</hi> when <hi>Gods Name</hi> is by none more blaſphemed and diſhonoured, then by thee and thy Comrades? Doeſt thou ſay, <hi>thy Kingdom come,</hi> when none is a greater enemy to the Kingdome of grace, and hath leſſe hope of the Kingdome of glory then thy ſelfe? Doeſt thou ſay, <hi>Thy Will be done in Earth as it is in Heaven,</hi> and yet when God tels thee, that 'tis his will that thou ſhouldſt <hi>follow peace with all men, and holineſſe,</hi> thou delighteſt in war and all manner of wickedneſſe, refuſing all juſt conditions of peace and adhortations to piety? Doeſt thou ſay <hi>Give us this day our daily bread,</hi> and yet takeſt away by violence and rapine, all the bread and other neceſſaries of life, that thy poore brother hath laboured for in the ſweat of his browes? Doeſt thou beſeech the Lord to <hi>forgive thee thy trespaſſes as thou forgiveſt them that treſpaſſe againſt thee,</hi> when as nothing but thy brothers blood will ſatisfie thee, and his too who ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver did, nor would have offended thee didſt not or hadſt not thou firſt beyond meaſure provoked him? Doeſt thou pray not to be <hi>led into temptation,</hi> and yet accounteſt it puſillani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity not to venture upon any thing, that thy luſts tempts thee unto? And doeſt thou ſupplicate to be <hi>delivered from all evill,</hi> and yet art never at reſt from plotting and practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing all the evill thy heart can invent, making it thy trade of life, to live all thy dayes in that evill of evils bloody warre? What is all this praying but a mocking of God, and blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:113301:13"/>of his Name; and how then can praying, or any other part of Gods ſervice, be performed as it ſhould in thoſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces where warres rage? when the actors in that bloody tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedy, being the onely men of power and ſway in thoſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, are ſo flatly oppoſite in all their practiſes to what is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by God or deſired from him; I but will ſome Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers of theſe times ſay, you are quite miſtaken in us, we doe not uſe the <hi>Lords Prayer</hi> at all, but we pray onely as the <hi>Spirit</hi> teacheth us: but what <hi>Spirit</hi> is it. I beſeech them? Whoſe teaching they follow in their prayers, when they lay aſide and deſpiſe the <hi>prayers</hi> which the Lord Chriſt himſelfe hath <hi>taught</hi> them? Certainly 'tis not that <hi>Spirit</hi> of God which <hi>helpeth our infirmities, and when we know not what we ſhould pray for as we ought, doth it ſelfe make interceſſion for us with groanings which cannot be uttered, Rom.</hi> 8.26. For that <hi>Spirit</hi> would never teach men to contemne and reject that <hi>prayer</hi> Chriſt by the ſame <hi>Spirit</hi> hath taught them, but on the contrary would ſo inſtruct and quicken them in their powring forth that and other prayers, now ſlighted by them, that the uſing thereof once would more effectually prevaile with God, and more feelingly comfort themſelves then all the vaine tedious tautologiſing bablings, that ever fall from them; beſides men taught by that <hi>Spirit</hi> would ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre to appeare in any acts ſo repugnant to each clauſe of that <hi>prayer.</hi> I confeſſe for my ſhare, that, as where I call to minde the reigning ſinnes of theſe times, ſuch as <hi>blindneſſe of heart, pride, vaine glory, and hypociſie, envy, hatred, malice,</hi> and all manner of <hi>uncharitableneſſe, fornication, and other</hi> ſuch like <hi>deadly ſinnes, ſedition, and privy conſpiracy, falſe do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and hereſie, hardneſſe of heart and contempt of Gods Word and Commandement, &amp;c.</hi> I doe not wonder to ſee and heare of ſuch multitudes, that ſtartle at our ſet formes of publike prayer, wherein theſe ſinnes are ſet forth, ript up and prayed againſt with ſo much plainneſſe of expreſſion and no leſſe vehemency and ardency of devotion, and to deſire ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:113301:14"/>to uſe ſome looſe prayers of their owne, wherein they may take their owne liberty, and pray againſt thoſe ſinnes as frees any ſuit whereof others are guilty, not themſelves. So when I obſerve of what <hi>spirit</hi> many men are, calling dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for <hi>fire from heaven</hi> upon their fellow brethren, or ſtirring up what fire earth and hell can helpe them to kindle a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, I doe not admire that even the <hi>Lords prayer</hi> alſo is, which is compoſed of a <hi>ſpirit</hi> ſo much contrary to theirs, laid aſide by them. But 'tis a ſad caſe in the interim, that ſhould either be given up to ſuch a reprobate mind, or live the leaſt time in ſuch an ungodly courſe of life, as not to dare to uſe that forme of <hi>prayer</hi> which Chriſt hath preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, or if they doe, their very uſing thereof proves no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then a mocking or an abuſing of him that preſcribed it. I doe not condemne all Souldiers, nor all ſouldiers prayers, the <hi>faith</hi> of that <hi>Centurion</hi> in the <hi>Goſpell,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 8. <hi>Acts</hi> 10.</note> and the <hi>prayers</hi> of <hi>that Centurion</hi> in the <hi>Acts,</hi> and the <hi>faith</hi> and <hi>prayers</hi> of many devout ſouldiers both before and ſince, would riſe up in judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt me, if I ſhould ſo judge them and their devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: but the more devout ſouldiers are, the more they will aſſent to truth propugned by me, that warres are an enemy to publike devotion, whatſoever interruption, private praiers ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer by them; I doe confeſſe, we doe not read that ever <hi>David</hi> was more fervent or frequent in his prayers, then when he was encompaſſed or purſued by his warlike enemies; but then it muſt be alſo acknowledged, that even in thoſe times, <hi>David</hi> prayed for nothing more then for ſuch times, wherein he might againe, as formerly he had in times of peace,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 42. <hi>Pſal,</hi> 84.</note> preſent both himſelfe and his prayers to God in <hi>Gads houſe, has holy Temple or Sanctuary,</hi> the place of publike wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Scythians,</hi> who as <hi>Herodotus</hi> reports of them, did wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip very many Gods, did erect neither Temple, Altar, nor ſtatute to any God, ſave onely <hi>Mars</hi> the God of warre, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timating, that where warres are predominant, there all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:113301:14"/>publike worſhip and ſevice of God or whatſoever is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led God is quite caſhiered. This we finde in ſacred records the <hi>Prophets</hi> prophecying to the <hi>Jews</hi> the free liberty &amp; happy en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying of Gods publike worſhip &amp; ſervice amongſt them, did commonly join with it or rather promiſe before it, ſome pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of <hi>peace, Iſa.</hi> 52.7. a place even now cited, <hi>How beautifull upon the mountaines are the feet of him that bringeth good ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, that publiſheth peace, &amp;c.</hi> &amp; then follows v. 8. <hi>Thy watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſhall lift up the voice, &amp;c.</hi> There is little or no lifting up of the <hi>voice</hi> of <hi>watch-men</hi> to be excepted in any place till <hi>peace</hi> be proclaimed. So <hi>Nahum,</hi> 1.15. <hi>Behole upon the mountains the feet of him that bringeth good tidings that pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſheth peace,</hi> then followes, <hi>O Judah keep thy ſolemne feaſts, performe thy vow,</hi> where <hi>peace</hi> is, there the publike worſhip and ſervice of God may be performed with ſome ſolmnity; but where <hi>peace</hi> is not, though men ſhould divote them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to it never ſo much, yet they cannot performe it with any ſolemnity, nay ſcarce with any tolerable reverence: if then there were no other reaſon of <hi>praying for the peace of Jeruſalem,</hi> but its being the place of Gods publike worſhip and ſervice, that alone is ſufficient to ingage any man in that duty that deſire to worſhip and ſerve God as he ſhould.</p>
            <p>But then confider <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> as it is alſo the ſeat of juſtice and judgment, and ſo the force of the argument for the <hi>pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the peace</hi> thereof is in a manner doubled; <hi>let judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> (ſaith the <hi>Prophet Amos) run downe as waters and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe as a mighty ſtreame Cap.</hi> 5.24. that is, let juſtice and judgment have their free courſe, and run in their owne channell without chick, ſtop, or outlet; now that cannot be but where God is pleaſed to grant <hi>peace</hi> to a place, if God do not <hi>extend peace</hi> to a place <hi>as a river Iſa.</hi> 66.12. Juſtice and Judgement can never run downe there as a ſtreame: <hi>Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe and peace</hi> (ſaith the <hi>Pſalmiſt) have kiſſed each other, Pſal.</hi> 85.10. ('tis as true of this Righteouſneſſe and peace whereof we are now diſcourſing as of any) and ſince they firſt
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:113301:15"/>greeted, it can never be found, where ever this Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe was without <hi>peace,</hi> though this <hi>peace</hi> hath been in many places without Righteouſneſſe. Juſt and ſtrickt diſcipline may be and is obſerved in warre, ſo farre as it may advantage either the deſigne in hand or the whole Armies ſafety, or the Commanders honour; but for common juſtice equally com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municating it ſelfe unto all men, 'tis onely to be ſound where <hi>peace</hi> is, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (ſaith <hi>Maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus Tyrius</hi>) warre is the teacher or maſter of injuſtice. In warres, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c. (as that woman complaines in <hi>Homer</hi>) they, kill men, they fire Cities into ruinous heapes, they lead away women and children into captivity; or as <hi>Tacitus</hi> deſcribed the iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of a warre waged by <hi>Antonius,</hi> and is found true of all warres, <hi>Non dignitas non at as protegebat, quo minus ſtupra cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibus, caeda ſtupris miſcerentur, &amp;c.</hi> neither honour, nor age, nor ought elſe did protect any, but rapes, warre mingled with murders, and murders with rapes; hoarihared men, and ſuperanuated women, eſteemed not worthy to be made a prey or ſpoyle, were drawn and dragged up and downe the ſtreets for ſport and paſtime, and young and tender Virgins, together with youthes of any comelineſſe and feature, were even torne in peices by the luſtfull Souldiers, and the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers themſelves, many of them ſlaine in their luſts by their owne fellowes, burning in the ſame luſts with them. O the injuſtice of warre, 'tis not to be expreſſed with juſt expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons! 'tis a <hi>maxime</hi> of warre, <hi>quodcunque libet facere victori licet;</hi> 'tis lawfull for the victor to doe what him pleaſeth, and victor or not victor, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (as <hi>Euri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pides</hi> hath it) he is accounted an ill Souldier that does not ſome miſchiefe; and if any that are injured or abuſed, prove ſo ridiculous or rather ſo mad as to complaine thereof, either to the Generall or to ſome ſubordinate Commander, the beſt anſwer they can expect, is that of <hi>Caeſar</hi> to <hi>Metellus,</hi> when <hi>Metellus</hi> urged certaine lawes for not taking away
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:113301:15"/>the money in <hi>Saturnes Temple,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>). The time of warre is no time for obſerving lawes or that of <hi>Caius Marius</hi> to ſome that accuſed him and his Souldiers of great wrongs, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. I cannot heare (ſaith he) the lawes for the noiſe of Armes the ratling of drums, and the roaring of Ordnance, ſilence the lawes &amp; ſtrike the very Judges them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves deafe: If then it were but for <hi>Jeruſalems</hi> being the ſeat or place of juſtice there being the <hi>Thrones</hi> of <hi>judgment, the Thrones of the houſe of David; Jeruſalem</hi> deſerved, and ſo doe all ſuch places ſtill, the beſt prayers and prayers of the beſt for the <hi>peace</hi> thereof.</p>
            <p>Thus you have been ſhowne the deſirableneſſe of <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lems peace</hi> as <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> is taken litterally for that place which God had made choice of, to be the place of his publike wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and ſervice, and the ſeat of juſtice and judgement; now take <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> in the miſtery, as it ſignifies <hi>Gods Church</hi> in what place or places ſoever it be planted or diſperſed, and ſo the arguments for the deſirableneſſe of <hi>Ieruſalems peace</hi> may be doubled and trebled; but I ſhall for the preſent chooſe rather to give you the application of what hath been delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and reſerve my meditations on the <hi>peace</hi> of <hi>Gods Church,</hi> till I have liberty to enlarge them to ſome proportion befit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting that ſubject.</p>
            <p>If the peace of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> as <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> is taken for the place of Gods publike worſhip and ſervice, and the ſeat of juſtice and judgement were then, and ſo the peace of all ſuch places is ſtill, a thing moſt deſirable worthy of the beſt pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>In the firſt place, you may from hence learn what to think of them in part who goe about to diſturbe the peace of ſuch places, yea and to baniſh if it were in their power, all peace from them; I ſay you may from hence learne what to thinke in part of ſuch, for what heart ſo large, what thought ſo vaſt, as to be able to comprehend what they deſerve in the totall?
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:113301:16"/>
               <hi>Bleſſed</hi> (ſaith our <hi>Saviour</hi>) <hi>are the Peace-makers for they ſhall be called the Children of God, Math.</hi> 5.9. And if the <hi>Peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makers</hi> are bleſſed, we may conclude by the law of contraries that ſurely the peace diſturbers are accurſed, and if they ſhall be called the <hi>Children of God,</hi> theſe may be called the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the divell. And indeed none but ſuch curſed chidren of that accurſed father, would ever have attempted the diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing of the peace of thoſe places, wherein God is ſolemnly worſhipped, and juſtice and judgement duly executed. For what is the <hi>glory</hi> and <hi>ſtrength</hi> of a Nation but theſe two; the worſhip and ſervice of God rightly performed, and juſtice and judgment faithfully adminiſtred? <hi>The glory is departed from Iſrael</hi> (ſaith the wife of <hi>Phineas</hi>) <hi>for the Arke of God is taken,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 4.22. The <hi>Arke</hi> of God, being the ſigne of Gods preſence amongſt the people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> is ſtiled the <hi>glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Iſriel:</hi> And what doth now manifeſt Gods preſence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt any people ſo evideutly and lively as the true worſhip and ſervice of God doth? Nay what is there but that which makes God to be preſent amongſt any people? God himſelf I confeſſe, or the preſence of God amongſt a people, is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly the <hi>glory</hi> of that Nation, ſo <hi>Ierem.</hi> cals him, 2.11. <hi>My people have changed their glory for that as doth not profit;</hi> ſo the <hi>Pſalmiſt, Pſ.</hi> 106.20. <hi>Thus they changed their glory, &amp;c.</hi> But this name may by a <hi>metonimia</hi> be aſcribed alſo to that which is the ſigne of Gods preſence, and ſo as well to Gods worſhip and ſervice now, as ever it was to the <hi>Arke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that Gods worſhip and ſervice is alſo the <hi>ſtrength</hi> of a Nation as well as the <hi>glory,</hi> no other Teſtimony need be produced then that, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 11.17. <hi>ſo they ſtrengthened the Kingdome of</hi> Judah, <hi>and made</hi> Rehoboam <hi>the ſon of</hi> Solomon <hi>ſtrong three yeeres, for three yeeres they walked in the way of</hi> David <hi>and</hi> Solomon, that is, they worſhipped and ſerved the Lord as <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Solomon</hi> had done.</p>
            <p>Then that the executing of juſtice and judgment is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe both a <hi>ſtrength</hi> and a <hi>glory</hi> to that Nation that is bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:113301:16"/>therewith, may be ſeen ſufficiently, either <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1. from v. 17. to the end of v. 27. or Cap. 9.7. It being declared in the latter place, that a Kingdome is both ordered and eſtabliſhed by juſtice and judgement, and in the former, that the want thereof is a main cauſe of a Kingdomes ruine. Now this being cleared, that the worſhip and ſervice of God rightly perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and juſtice and judgment faithfully adminiſtred, are both the <hi>glory</hi> and the <hi>ſtrength</hi> of a Nation; and it being at large demonſtrated, that neither of theſe can be performed where <hi>peace</hi> is not preſerved; what can we conclude leſſe of thoſe that labour to undermine and blow up the <hi>peace</hi> of a Nation, wherein both thoſe rich gemmes of a Nations <hi>glory,</hi> and firme pillars of her <hi>ſtrength</hi> are, then that they are <hi>Traytors</hi> to that Church and ſtate? It deſerves to be reputed treaſon againſt a Kingdome, if any of that Kingdom eſpecially, ſhould attempt ought againſt the <hi>peace</hi> of it, though the ſound of Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and ſervice hath ſcarce been ever heard therein; of ſuch unſpeakeable worth and excellency is <hi>peace</hi> it ſelfe: of what brand then are they worthy, that have attempted the utter ruine of a Nations <hi>peace,</hi> (I need not name the Nation) wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in God hath beene longer and more eminently worſhipped and ſerved (to his glory not ours be it ſpoken) and juſtice and judgement more ſtrictly and duely executed, then in any one Nation whatſoever? To call their crime high treaſon is too low a terme for it; for take the crime in its true altitude, and you'le finde, that it reacheth from hell where it was firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trived, to Heaven it ſelfe, againſt which it is complotted and ſo 'tis high treaſon to the ſtretch of height, being treaſon againſt the moſt higheſt. Every one ſees, or at leaſt may if he doe not ſhut his owne eyes or ſuffer others to blindfold him, that the ſacred Perſon of our moſt gracious Soveraign and ſome of the beſt of His blood, &amp; divers of His Nobility, are (for what they lately have been I tremble to recall) in imminent danger on the one part, and the repreſentative body of the Kingdome (as they themſelves declare themſelves) are but in little leſſe
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:113301:17"/>hazard on the other; and for ought any that are beſt skilled in Armes know, ere the ſword be put up againe, the whole Kingdom may be ruined. And this one would think is treaſon high enough, to contrive all theſe into ſo much perill, the Lord diſcover the contrivers whoſoever they be.</p>
            <p>But alas who, who ſees or is able to conceive, what blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy againſt God and Chriſt, what ſcandall to <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> it ſelfe, will from hence be occaſioned and that too too juſtly? For what firſt will the Heathen and other In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidels ſay? Are theſe the Chriſtians? are theſe they that glory ſo much in their Lord Chriſt, and call themſelves after his Name? Why they tell us, that Chriſt was no warrier, no fighter, no revenger, no ſpiller of blood, &amp;c. but was the <hi>Prince of peace, whoſe government and peace</hi> is inſeparable, as well as endleſſe; they tell us that Chriſt did no <hi>violence</hi> to any, no nor ſo much as <hi>opened his mouth</hi> when he was afflicted and oppreſſed himſelfe, but was <hi>led as a lambe to the ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and as a ſheepe that is dumbe before her ſhearers.</hi> They would make us beleeve alſo, that Chriſt came into the world to make <hi>peace</hi> betweene the world and his Father, and that at his comming the very <hi>Angels ſang</hi> of <hi>peace on Earth,</hi> and that all the time of his being here on earth he preacht <hi>peace,</hi> and a little before his returne to heaven he <hi>prayed for peace,</hi> and at his very leaving his Diſciples, he <hi>left peace with them</hi> as his laſt legacy; but he that ſhould obſerve how little theſe <hi>Chriſtians</hi> regard <hi>peace,</hi> and how ſmall a thing will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke them to ſpill one anothers blood, to teare out one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers throat, or to doe one another any miſchiefe, cannot be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve that themſelves doe beleeve their <hi>Lord Chriſt</hi> to have been ſuch a <hi>peace-maker, peace-preacher,</hi> and <hi>peace-practiſer,</hi> as they ſay he was. They call themſelves <hi>Chriſts ſheepe</hi> and Chriſt their <hi>Shepheard,</hi> but did ever any man ſee ſheep ſo worrey and devour one another? Why Wolves or Tygers, Beares or Lyons cannot deale more cruelly with one another then they doe. They call themſelves the <hi>Vine-branches</hi> and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:113301:17"/>Chriſt their <hi>Vine;</hi> but was it ever heard that Vine-branches did gall, oppreſſe and vex one another as they doe? Why briars and thornes doe not ſcratch and raſe one another halfe ſo much. They ſay they are all <hi>members</hi> of one and the ſame body, but did ever any members of one and the ſame body ſo fight and quarrell with one another, ſo mangle and martyr one another? They ſay they are ſervants to one and the ſame Lord, but did ever fellow-ſervants ſo beat and butcher one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother? They ſay they have all but one <hi>faith,</hi> but would any man thinke they had any faith at all, when they ſeeke to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plant and ruine one another ſo as they doe? They ſay they are all baptiſed into one <hi>baptiſme,</hi> but he that obſerves how they delight in one anothers deſtruction, might well doubt whether they were dipt or beſprinkled with the <hi>blood of the Lambe</hi> as they give out, or with the blood of ſome beaſt of prey? They ſay they eat all of the ſame <hi>spirituall meat,</hi> and <hi>drink all of the ſame spirituall drink,</hi> and indeed amongſt us <hi>Heathen,</hi> the eating together at one table is to us a ſtrong tie of friendſhip, and ſome of us as the <hi>Scythians</hi> by name have accounted no obligation greater for the ingaging us in all firmneſſe of love and fidelity each to other, then the taſting together a little blood in the ſame cup; but as for theſe <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,</hi> neither eating together at their <hi>Lords table,</hi> and that of that <hi>bread</hi> which they ſay <hi>came downe from heaven,</hi> can qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et their riſing ſtomacks, nor their drinking together of that cup, which they acknowledge to be the cup of the <hi>new Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant in Chriſts blood,</hi> can allay their fiery ſpirits, from taking up Armes one againſt another, to the ſpilling each others blood. One of their <hi>Apoſtles</hi> tels them, that 'tis <hi>a ſhame for them to goe to law with one another,</hi> eſpecially <hi>before</hi> us <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidels,</hi> but they are not aſhamed to goe to warre with one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, and that before us or any elſe. In a word they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine of us <hi>Heathen,</hi> for <hi>offering</hi> our <hi>ſonnes and</hi> our <hi>daughters</hi> in ſacrifice to <hi>devils,</hi> and yet they ſacrifice daily their ſonnes and daughters and themſelves and al to their own diviliſh ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:113301:18"/>and revenge. Aſſuredly theſe practiſes will never gaine us to be of their profeſſion, and either let them tell us of ſome other <hi>Chriſt,</hi> or let them never tell us that they are <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,</hi> for we ſhall be <hi>Infidels</hi> (as they call us) in that too, as in other things, till we ſee a better agreement betwixt Chriſts actions and theirs, and betwixt their owne profeſſion and practiſes. Thus is Chriſt and <hi>Chriscianity blaſphemed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Heathen;</hi> and what think you will our adverſaries the <hi>Papiſts</hi> ſay? Nay what will they not ſay that is evill both of us and our Religion? I dare not ſpeake what they will ſay leſt ſome ſhould ſay that I taught them what to ſpeake; but I will be hold to tell you what ſome of them have ſaid upon leſſe occaſion, as Doctor <hi>Kelliſon</hi> by name in his <hi>ſurvey of new Religion lib.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. <hi>ſect.</hi> 4.5. The reformers (as he cals us) urge nothing ſo much as that we muſt obey Princes and their injunctions, but this they doe onely when Eccleſiaſticall pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er calls them to an account, or when the Princes lawes doe favouriſe their doctrine; and if any doe marke their procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings they ſhall ſee that they honour not Authority, but love their herefies, (as that railing <hi>Romanist</hi> calls our orthodox opinions) which if Princes will not like, then they contemne and deſpiſe all Authority, and will not let to make a mutiny, and ſtir up Subjects to rebellion; thus that foule mouth hath ſlandered us and our Religion upon no occaſion given no not the leaſt, for he feigns the occaſion upon the Proteſtants carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age towards Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> which to the eternall honor of our Proteſtant Religion in generall, and to the perpetuall renown of the anciently religious Proteſtants within the Counties of <hi>Suffolk</hi> and <hi>Norfolk</hi> in particular, was ſo humbly and faithfully loyall, as it could not well be tranſcended; and what thinke you then will ſuch bold calumniators caſt on us and our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, now upon theſe ſad and unnaturall differences and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions betweene our moſt pious Sovereigne and his Great Councell? I mourne to thinke what a ſcandall our Religion is like to undergoe, unleſſe God doe miraculouſly interpoſe
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:113301:18"/>and compoſe thoſe diſtractions. <hi>Offences muſt come, but woe be unto them</hi> whoſoever they are <hi>by whom the offence cometh,</hi> eſpecially ſuch an offence as brings with it a ſcandall upon Religion. <hi>O pray then for the peace of our Jeruſalem;</hi> and pray that the prime diſturbers thereof may be diſcovered whoſoever they are, and then I am confident, the Papiſts mouthes will be ſtopt from charging the Proteſtants with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion againſt their Prince: for whatſoever they ſhall pleaſe to call our preſent diviſion, (as leſſe then rebellion who can call it, that would not ſuffer his tongue to rebell againſt his heart, or both againſt God and his King?) It will appeare upon diſcovery of the Authors thereof, that they themſelves, eſpecially the Jeſuits and their old friends the Anabaptiſts, together with the Browniſts and other <hi>Sectaries,</hi> like <hi>Samp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons foxes</hi> tied together by the tailes, though their heads look contrary wayes, have been the maine, if not the onely incen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diaries of theſe our never-ſufficiently to be deplored tumults and inſurrections; but I ſhall not trouble my ſelfe or you further about this deep-laid and high-raiſed iniquity. <hi>They encourage themſelves in an evill matter, they commune of lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſnares privily, they ſay who ſhall ſee them? They ſearch out iniquities, they accompliſh a diligent ſearch, both the inward thought of every one of them, and the heart is deep, but God ſhal ſhoot at them with an arrow, ſuddainly ſhall they be wounded, ſo they ſhall make their owne tongue to fall upon themſelves, all that ſee them ſhall flee away, and all men ſhall fear and declare the worke of God, for they ſhall wiſely conſider of his doing, Pſal.</hi> 64, And then though the crime it ſelfe may want a name, yet the Actors and complotters thereof, at leaſt the chiefe of them, will not want for ſuch vengeance, as we hope ſhall terrifie others from ever attempting the like horrid en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, we may from hence alſo be informed what to judge of thoſe, who if they have not been the firſt movers, or prime contrivers in the betraying the bleſſed peace of this
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:113301:19"/>Nation, wherein God hath been ſo ſolemnly worſhipped and ſerved, and juſtice and judgement ſo duly executed, yet they have been too great encouragers and abettors of ſuch traytors.</p>
            <p>It was a complaint taken up by <hi>Eraſmus</hi> againſt ſome <hi>Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy-men</hi> in his time and in the times not long before him, that when any <hi>Princes</hi> were inclinable to warres, <hi>Alius e ſacro ſuggeſto promittit omnium admiſſorum condonationem, &amp;c.</hi> One (ſaies he) promiſeth from the ſacred pulpit, pardon of all offences whatſoever, to all ſuch as will fight under ſuch or ſuch Princes banners, <hi>Alius clamat invictiſſime Princeps,</hi> ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cries out moſt mighty Prince, doe but you hold your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, for the favouring of this Religion, and God ſhall fight for you, <hi>Alius promittit certam victoriam, propheta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum voces ad rem impiam detorquens,</hi> another he promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth certaine victory, wreſting the very ſayings of the holy Prophets to that moſt unholy buſineſſe, <hi>Tam bellaces concio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes audivimus Monachorum, Theologorum, &amp;c.</hi> ſuch warlike Sermons (ſaith that Author) have we heard from <hi>Monks</hi> and other Divines; and I would we had never heard the like from ſome of our Preachers; have not ſome of our Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of late, runne up and downe from pulpit to pulpit and there lifted up their voices like <hi>Trumpets,</hi> not to ſhew the <hi>people their tranſgreſſion and the houſe of</hi> Jacob <hi>their ſinnes,</hi> which they have a commiſſion for, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58.1. but to ſound an alarme, and to incite to warre; for which I beleeve they have no particular Commiſſion, and their generall Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on I am ſure is quite contrary, they being ſent to proclaime and publiſh and ſo to incite unto and perſwade peace and not warres: One he cryes out in <hi>Moſes</hi> words, <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.29. <hi>conſecrate your ſelves to day to the Lord, even every man upon his ſonne and upon his brother, &amp;c.</hi> forgetting that though he be allowed to ſit in <hi>Moſes ſeat,</hi> yet the uſe of <hi>Moſes</hi> ſword is denied him, much leſſe hath he the command there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; beſides <hi>Moſes</hi> though he were the ſupreme Magiſtrate, urged a particular command from God for what he then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:113301:19"/>unto v. 27. whereas this <hi>Levit</hi> excluded all Magiſtracy, cannot ſhew the leaſt authority ſo much as from <hi>Moſes</hi> for what he cals for. Another makes bold with <hi>Davids</hi> words 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 22.16. <hi>Ariſe and be doing; ariſe and be doing?</hi> What I beſeech him? Would he have the people build an <hi>houſe</hi> to the Lord? For it was to that purpoſe that <hi>David</hi> uſed thoſe words to his ſon <hi>Solomon:</hi> I am afraid <hi>Gods houſe</hi> is not ſo well beloved of him; no, rather ariſe and be pulling downe <hi>Gods houſe,</hi> orariſe and be plundering thy neighbours houſe: this I beleeve comes ſomewhat neere his meaning, I am ſure as neere as his does <hi>Davids.</hi> A third ecchoes forth that bitter curſe of the <hi>Angel</hi> of the Lord againſt <hi>Meroz. Iudg.</hi> 5.23. <hi>Curſe ye Meroz (ſaid the Angel of the Lord) curſe ye bitterly the Inhabitants thereof, becauſe they came not to the help of the Lord, to the help of the Lord againſt the mighty.</hi> And obſerve how pertinently and punctually he applies it; the caſe of the <hi>Merozits</hi> as you may read <hi>Iudg. cap</hi> 4. and 5. ſtood thus, <hi>Iabin King of Canaan</hi> with his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple the <hi>Canaanites</hi> farre <hi>greater</hi> and <hi>mightier</hi> then <hi>Iſrael,</hi> had <hi>twenty yeers together mightily oppreſſed Iſrael;</hi> then <hi>Deborah a Propheteſſe in Iſrael,</hi> and one that was ſupreme <hi>Iudge</hi> in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> at that time, upon a particular expreſſe command from God (beſides Gods general command long before given for the <hi>utter deſtroying</hi> of the <hi>Canaanites</hi> &amp; making no <hi>covenant with them, and ſhewing no mercy to them, Deu.</hi> 7.1, 2.) cals to <hi>Barak to gather together ten thouſand men of the Children of Naptha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> and <hi>Zebulum,</hi> the two Tribes that were neeereſt him, and to encounter with <hi>Iabins</hi> mighty Hoſt at ſuch a place, aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring him that the <hi>Lord</hi> would <hi>deliver that great Hoſt into his hand.</hi> Now becauſe the <hi>Merozites</hi> were neere at hand, and yet would not come out and ſhew themſelves in the aſſiſting and helping forward this deſigne, thus commanded by the <hi>Lord</hi> (whatſoever cauſe elſe there were unrevealed) the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel of the Lord</hi> denounced this heavy curſe againſt them ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>curſe ye Meroz, curſe ye bitterly the Inhabitants therof, &amp;c.</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:113301:20"/>againſt them, I ſay, the <hi>Angel</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> denounced this curſe, and againſt them onely, though ſundry other Tribes came not out to this help beſides them, as <hi>Ruben who abode among the ſheepefolds,</hi> and <hi>Gilead</hi> or <hi>Manaſſch, who abode be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond Iordan,</hi> and <hi>Dan who remained in ſhips,</hi> and <hi>Aſher who continued on the ſea ſhore and abode in his breaches, Iudg.</hi> 5.16.17. None of theſe came to this <hi>help of the Lord,</hi> and yet they were at the moſt but reproved or marked for it by the <hi>spirit</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> not curſed by the <hi>Angel of the Lord</hi> as the <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rozites</hi> were. Now compare our preſent caſe with theirs; doth any Idolatrous King and his people, farre more mighty and potent then we, oppreſſe our <hi>Iſrael?</hi> Are he and his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, ſuch as are commanded by Gods command, to be utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſtroyed and no covenant to be made with them, nor mercy ſhewn them? Or is there any expreſſe particular com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand from the Lord at this preſent, for the raiſing an Army againſt them, with an aſſured promiſe of victory over them? And doth the ſupreme <hi>Iudge</hi> in our <hi>Iſrael</hi> call to any to put this command in execution? Let all theſe or any of theſe be ſhewne, and when they are, let him blame thoſe that doe not <hi>come to the help of the Lord:</hi> but let him then alſo take heed of curſing any more of them, then the <hi>Angel</hi> of the Lord commandes him to curſe, leſt the curſe fall upon his owne head for curſing Gods owne <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and perverting Gods Word to the juſtifying his owne curſing contrary to Gods command. A fourth, he thunders out that curſe <hi>Ier.</hi> 48.10. <hi>Curſed be he that keepeth back his ſword from blood;</hi> but from what blood doth he meane? Doth he meane from the blood of <hi>Moabites,</hi> whoſe King had formerly hired <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laam</hi> to curſe Gods <hi>Iſrael, Numb.</hi> 22. and whoſe daughters had tempted <hi>Iſrael</hi> to commit whoredome with them, to the great provoking of the Lord againſt them, <hi>Numb.</hi> 25? Doth he mean from the blood of <hi>Moabites,</hi> whoſe Kings and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple both, had at ſundry times ſorely oppreſſed <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and are now themſelves, for thoſe and other their impieties, deſtined
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:113301:20"/>to utter ruine by an expreſſe decree from the Lord? Doth, he I ſay, meane the blood of ſuch when he rends his throat with roaring out a curſe againſt thoſe that ſhall <hi>keepe back their ſword from blood?</hi> If ſo, he doth in ſomething reſemble the <hi>Prophet;</hi> yet 'tis not unknowne to a meane Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, that the <hi>Prophets</hi> are not to be imitated in every thing which they did or ſaid; witneſſe <hi>Elijah's</hi> act in cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling for fire from Heaven. 2 <hi>King.</hi> 1. which when the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Chriſt would have imitated, Chriſt ſeverely rebuked them for it, <hi>Luk.</hi> 9.54, 55. But alas is it not other blood that this blood-hound hunts after? Is it not the blood of Chriſtians? Is it not the blood of Proteſtants? Is it not the blood of thoſe that are of the ſame blood with us? Nay, I pray God the beſt blood amongſt us, the <hi>Blood Royall</hi> it ſelfe be not too much hankered after by him. I am ſure the ſword would put but little difference, and the bullet leſſe, betwixt that and other blood in a common battell, did not the Lord both of ſword, bullet, and battell, in his more then ordinary love and care of ſuch blood, guide them all other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then bloody men aime and intend them. Beſides to whom is this charge given, not to <hi>hold back the ſword from blood</hi> upon perill of a curſe, for that's alſo worthy our taking notice? Is it to the <hi>Heathen</hi> ſuch as the <hi>Babylonians</hi> were, to whom the <hi>Prophet</hi> there ſpeakes, or (as ſome Expoſitors would have it) who are there brought in by the <hi>Prophet</hi> as ſpeaking it themſelves? No 'tis to <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> tis to Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, 'tis to <hi>Engliſh-men,</hi> that this new Prophet ſpeakes; he would have us, for whom Chriſt was <hi>made a curſe,</hi> and ſhed his own moſt <hi>precious blood to reconcile us to God,</hi> think our ſelves to be accurſed if we ſhould with-hold our ſwords from that curſed act of ſhedding one anothers blood. Well then may learned and pious <hi>O Ecolampadius</hi> his intimation given upon thoſe very words, be made our obſervation. <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditioſi hunc verſum pro ſe trahunt, ſed declarant, quod Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonijs ſimiles ſint, imo licet dicas inferiores, quod nullum ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beant
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:113301:21"/>mandatum a domino, &amp;c.</hi> Seditious men wreſt this verſe to ſerve their owne ſeditions humors; but they herein declare themſelves to be like the <hi>Babylontans,</hi> thoſe ſo much abominated cruell Heathen; nay thou maiſt ſay farre worſe then they, for that theſe have no command to take up thoſe words, which the <hi>Babylonians</hi> had. And thus what <hi>Ezekiel</hi> ſaid of the Prophets of <hi>Jeruſalem, Ezek.</hi> 22.25, 28. is found by wofull experience, too true of too many of the Prophets of this Nation, <hi>There is a conspiracy of her Prophets in the midſt thereof, like a roaring lyon ravening the prey; they have devoured ſoules, they have taken the treaſure and precious things, they have made her many widowes in the midſt thereof. They have dawbed</hi> her Princes <hi>with untempered morter, ſeeing vanity, and divining lies unto them, ſaying, thus ſaith the Lord God, when the Lord hath not spoken.</hi> Or to take up the complaint of the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah, Cap.</hi> 5. v. 30, 31. <hi>A wonderfull and horrible thing is committed in the Land,</hi> the <hi>Prophets propheſie falſly, and the Prieſts beare rule,</hi> or as it is in the margin, <hi>take into their hands by their meanes, and my people love to have it ſo, and what will ye doe in the end thereof?</hi> What will ye doe in the end thereof? Nay, I leave that to God to diſpoſe, and to you to expect. Onely for further caution to my ſelfe and fellow-preachers, ſuffer me in a word more, to ſhew how ill-beſeeming and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>congruous, if not wicked and pernitious, it is for us Preachers of the <hi>Gospell,</hi> (ſuppoſe we did avoid thoſe groſſe exorbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tances now mentioned) to encourage to warres, unleſſe we have ſome ſpeciall calling from God thereunto. For what hath a Preacher of the <hi>Gospell of peace</hi> to do with war, except it be to preach againſt it? 'Tis ſaid, that by the Law a <hi>Prieſt</hi> ſhould not have his vote in a cauſe of blood: I am ſure 'tis incongruous (to ſay the leaſt of it) that a Miniſter, who is commanded both to pray daily in the Congregation, <hi>Give peace in our time O Lord,</hi> and to diſmiſſe the Congregation with a benediction of peace, <hi>The peace of God which paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:113301:21"/>all underſtanding keepe your hearts, &amp;c.</hi> ſhould have his voice ſo deepe in blood, as to encourage any to the waging of warre; wherein the blood not of one or two, but of many thouſands is often ſpilt in one battell. <hi>Tune codem ore quo Chriſtum praedicas bellum laudas, cademque tuba Deum canis et ſatanam?</hi> Doeſt thou with one and the ſame mouth both preach Chriſt that great Peace-maker, that Prince of peace, and praiſe warre? What is that but with the ſame voice to trumpet forth the praiſe of God and of Satan? Whence didſt thou learne this Doctrine, or what example hadſt thou to preach ſuch? 'Tis certaine neither <hi>Chriſt</hi> nor his <hi>Apoſtles;</hi> for they ever taught and perſwaded to peace, as might be ſhewne by multitudes of examples, whereof thou canſt not be ignorant and yet thou wanteſt no ignorance. Take we heede then, we that are Preachers, (and ſo I winde up this leſſon) leſt whereas 'tis ſaid of the Preachers of the <hi>Gospell,</hi> (as you heard once, and againe) <hi>How beautifull are the feet of him that brings glad tidings, that publiſheth peace;</hi> the contrary be ſaid of any of us, How foul is the very tongue of ſuch or ſuch a Miniſter, that brings ſad tidings, that incites to warre; certainly ſuch a Preacher either miſtooke his cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, or his commiſſion, or both.</p>
            <p n="3">3 I have but a word more to adde, and that is a word of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation (for I am unwilling to leave you with a reproof) that you would be pleaſed to ſuffer your ſelves to obtaine what is, or ought to be, moſt deſired by you, your owne <hi>peace</hi> in the <hi>peace</hi> of our Nation; and to that end, that you would caſt not oyle, but water on that fire, which now threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens the conſumption, not of the <hi>Cedars</hi> of <hi>Lebanon</hi> alone but the very ſhrubs and brambles of the <hi>Forest,</hi> at leaſt be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded to with-hold what fuell you can from it, for feare your ſelves be ſuddenly made the fuell of it. You both ſee and heare, that unleſſe you purchaſe warre at a very deare rate, peace will follow you, though you doe not follow it. And doe you love blood heding ſo dearly, as that you will
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:113301:22"/>freely part with that, which at other times drops from you as ſo much of your blood, to help forward the ſpilling of others blood and your owne too? O the blindneſſe and mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſuch a people! none ſo blind as they that will not ſee, and none more mad, then they that ſtop their eares at the voice of the Charmer, charme he never ſo wiſely. Who hath bewitched you, or what people were ever thus beſotted? I cannot finde in all ſacred or prophane hiſtory, (that ever I ſet eye on) any example to parallell this. That obſtinate ſot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſhneſſe of the people of <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> ſet forth in a dialogue betwixt <hi>God</hi> and the <hi>Prophet Iſaiah Cap.</hi> 6.9, 10, 11, 12. comes the neereſt this, of any that I can remember; (I pray God it be not brought neerer in the concluſion) yet all this reſemblance is onely in generals; but for particulars I challenge all the encouragers to warre (and they will ſtreine hard for an example) to match it if they can; and 'tis a ſtrange obſtinacy, whereof no record can ſhew a preſident, nor any falſe prophet feigne one. O my beloved! (if I may call thoſe beloved that love not the <hi>peace of Jeruſalem</hi>) bethink your ſelves in time, leſt the Lord <hi>bring</hi> upon you <hi>the fruit of your thoughts, Jerem.</hi> 6.19. That as now, when <hi>the ſword of the</hi> Lord would in all probability be quiet,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 476.</note> and <hi>put up its ſelf into its ſcabbard,</hi> and <hi>reſt and be ſtill,</hi> ye will not ſuffer it,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>v,</hi> 7.</note> the Lord ere long <hi>give</hi> it a <hi>charge againſt</hi> you not to be quiet, till it have devoured at leaſt all thoſe who deſire that it may ſtill devour. The Husband-men call for <hi>peace,</hi> that they may now in their ſeaſon <hi>beat their ſwords into plowſheares, and their speares into pruning hookes.</hi> The Merchants and Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faring men call for <hi>peace,</hi> that they may now at their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed time, <hi>goe downe to the ſea in ſhips</hi> and <hi>doe buſineſſe in great waters,</hi> bringing a rich ſupply of all ſorts of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize from all parts of the world. The Tradeſ-men they call for <hi>peace,</hi> that they may recover their languiſhing tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ere the ſpirits thereof be quite ſpent. Wives and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren cry for <hi>peace,</hi> that they may not ſit as widowes and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:113301:22"/>Orphans lamenting the loſſe of their deare husbands and carefull fathers. All that are oppreſſed and wronged cry for <hi>peace,</hi> that the Judges of our Land, like <hi>Samuel</hi> in the <hi>dayes</hi> of <hi>peace,</hi> may keepe their conſtant circuites,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7. <hi>v.</hi> 14, 15, 16.</note> and judge their cauſes in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>onted places. All the faithfull and loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all hearted Subjects call for <hi>peace,</hi> that they may ſee <hi>their Lord the King delivered from the ſtrivings of the people,</hi> and <hi>brought back</hi> again to his <hi>houſe,</hi> and ſit on his throne in ſafety and honour. The King himſelfe cals for <hi>peace,</hi> that his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects may ſit under their owne vines, and under their owne figgetrees enjoying their wonted happineſſe accounted his. Nay the <hi>King of Kings</hi> here in our Text cals upon all theſe to call and cry to him for peace, that all theſe and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bleſſings which accompany <hi>peace,</hi> may once againe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to us and ſettle their abode amongſt us. Let us then in obedience to Gods command, if not in the ſenſe of our owne preſent condition, haſten unto with all ſpeed, and ply with all importunity, that <hi>Throne of grace</hi> to which we are thus graciouſly invited; and <hi>for Zions ſake</hi> let us <hi>not hold our peace, and for Jeruſalems ſake</hi> let us <hi>not rest, untill the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe</hi> and peace <hi>thereof goe forth as brightneſſe, and the ſalvation thereof as a lamp that burneth.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>Glory be to God in the highest, and on Earth peace, good will towards men.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
